<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[My Random Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[Essays, musings, and more by Cedric Amaya.]]></description><link>https://cedric.tech/blog</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Dec 2018 22:45:40 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[My Process of Building Side Projects]]></title><description><![CDATA[For those who don’t know, I’m a Computer Science major and I enjoy programming
outside of school and work. There’s something about getting…]]></description><link>https://cedric.tech/blog/building-side-projects/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://cedric.tech/blog/building-side-projects/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Dec 2018 23:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know, I’m a Computer Science major and I enjoy programming
outside of school and work. There’s something about getting to make whatever you
want while also having total ownership of a project that makes building side
projects so addicting. I’ve heard it compared to other hobbies such as gaming
or playing sports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although many side projects may go unfinished or unreleased,
I feel as though there is still a lot of experience to gain from simply starting
a project in the first place. In this post, I will walk you through my process
of coming up with an idea of what to make, taking said idea and turning it into
something tangible, to putting the project out in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we begin, I will warn you that my process is by no means perfect. As I’ll
discuss later, there are a few things I would like to do differently in the future
since my current process of building side projects can seem anomalous at times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Coming Up with an Idea 💡&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to build something, you first need an idea. I find this to be one of
the hardest parts of side projects. This is simply because if there is no idea,
there can’t be a project. To get around this potential roadblock, I like to
examine my own daily life and see what areas I could possibly speed up or
improve. Having intimate knowledge of the problem you’re trying to solve will
make building a side project that much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Preliminary Research 🧐&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once I have an idea in mind, I like to see what existing solutions already exist.
Now, if I find more than a few existing projects that solve the same issue that
I was hoping to tackle, then I usually will not continue with that project. This
is one of those situations that I mentioned earlier where I’m sort of peculiar—
the fact that there are already projects that try to solve an issue means that
your idea has already been validated—this is good news! Don’t be discouraged if
there are already other projects out there. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that if I do try to tackle such problems, I will often mimic the existing
projects’ solutions rather than building something unique. Although imitating one
project’s solution to help you solve an issue can be helpful, I have found that
relying too much on this method then makes it harder for me to build projects that
require unique and sophisticated solutions later on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Choosing a Tech Stack 🥞&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I have an idea and know I want to commit to this side project, the next
thing I do is research what tech stack I will use to turn the idea into a real
thing. This step assumes you’ve already determined the area or type of project
you are going to make—be it a browser extension, CLI tool, a web or mobile app,
etc. I love JavaScript and thanks to the run-time environment Node.js, I can make
projects as just about any application type. With the language selected, I then
will decide if I want to use any libraries that could help speed up the
development time and if I’m unfamiliar with a particular library, I will read
their documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Coding → MVP 🦴&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time for the fun part: coding! With an idea in mind and the right tools selected
to build said idea, I get to work. Programming can be a double-edged sword when
creating a side project: when it’s going well, I love it. But when I get stuck on
an issue that I can’t immediately solve, I also really hate it. Throughout the
development process, these two emotions can cycle between overpowering one
another. At times, I feel so defeated by a bug and want to give up entirely only
to get the biggest boost of confidence after stepping away and figuring out how
to squash the bug. I like to say making side projects can be like war—it’s
essentially a series of battles composed of wins and losses, me versus my code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually I come out victorious and emerge with something that works and solves
the original problem. This will almost always be a minimum viable product, or MVP.
The MVP serves as the skeleton for the finished product without all the bells and
whistles that will eventually make it complete.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Break from Code—Design Time 🎨&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the step in the process where I like to start thinking about how I will
market my side project while also giving myself a break from coding. Like a
newborn baby, the project needs a name. This can be as simple or extravagant as
you would like. Once a name is selected, I think about branding. What will the
main colors of the project be? What graphic or logo can best represent this
project? What font? Having answers to those questions then allows me to put my
creativity to use. Using design software (I’m a big fan of Sketch), I will put
together a press kit or package of promotional material (namely good-looking
graphics) to be used later on for open graph meta tags or product launches on
sites like Product Hunt or Reddit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Wrapping Up 🎀&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seem like a long process yet? Luckily, we’re just about done. After my creative
sprint, I go back to programming and flesh out the MVP. On goes the remaining
features I thought would be useful and any bug fixes that are critical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: there will always be bugs, so do not try to fix them all before launching
your product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Launching 🚀&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By now, I have a finished product and I’m ready to show it to the world. With the
press kit I made earlier, I hit up several relevant subreddits to the project I
just made and create posts that describe what the project is, why I made it, and
where to find it. Posting on Reddit will give my project some exposure and
feedback that I can then use to fix or tweak before launching on Product Hunt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Looking Ahead 🔭&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After having gone through this entire process several times and starting the
process but not finishing many more times, I feel as though there is room
for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, deciding whether or not to build something based on the number of
existing projects is kind of silly. Even if there are many solutions out there,
your take and solution to the problem is unique and therefore could end up
being a better solution than all the other projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, it’s really important to get your project out in the hands of the public
as soon as possible as this will significantly improve your chances of actually
completing it. Too many times to count have I worked on a project in isolation
without letting others try it which resulted in a “failed” launch. This is simply
due to the fact that I assumed I knew what people would want, rather than actually
letting them tell me. A costly mistake if you’re hoping to have users other than
yourself use the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what’s in store? I hope to work on the above issues while also continually
improving the process I’ve since been following. I feel as though the side
projects I’ve made up until this point have been quite small in scope, so in the
future I also plan on taking on larger problems that require more complex
solutions. Finally, I would love to make something that I can monetize and earn
some extra side income from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I already have some goals for 2019.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Advice for Beginners]]></title><description><![CDATA[Originally published on the r/learnprogrammig subreddit. For those struggling and comparing themselves to others… I’m right there with you…]]></description><link>https://cedric.tech/blog/advice-for-beginners/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://cedric.tech/blog/advice-for-beginners/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 15 Dec 2018 17:15:40 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published on the r/learnprogrammig subreddit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;For those struggling and comparing themselves to others…&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m right there with you. I’ve been programming for about three years now and
although I wouldn’t consider myself a beginner, I’m by no means an expert and
still feel like programming can be hard or that the code I write is shit. I
can’t help but see all of the other developers I follow on social media and
the projects they’re making and feel like I’ll never get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best advice I’ve heard until recently to dealing with this are sayings like
“don’t compare your beginning to someone else’s middle”. That makes sense and I
understood what it meant, but I was never really satisfied with when my “middle”
would manifest - I felt like no matter how many projects I made, I was not
progressing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is until I heard Ira Glass’ advice for beginners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply put, Glass describes the idea that there is a gap between our good taste
(the cool projects we aspire to one day write) and the stuff we actually make
(the code we write/the projects we’re actually making). The gap represents our
dissatisfaction with our work compared to the work that we aspire to someday
create.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t summarize Glass’ words in their full glory but luckily the transcript
isn’t too long, so I’ll paste it below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody tells this to people who are beginners, and I really wish somebody had&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;told this to me.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All of us who do creative work, we get into it because we have good taste. But&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;it’s like there is this gap. For the first couple years that you’re making&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;stuff, what you’re making isn’t so good. It’s not that great. It’s trying to&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;be good, it has ambition to be good, but it’s not that good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;But your taste, the thing that got you into the game, is still killer. And&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;your taste is good enough that you can tell that what you’re making is kind&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;of a disappointment to you. A lot of people never get past that phase. They&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;quit.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everybody I know who does interesting, creative work they went through years&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;where they had really good taste and they could tell that what they were&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;making wasn’t as good as they wanted it to be. They knew it fell short.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Everybody goes through that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;And if you are just starting out or if you are still in this phase, you gotta&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;know its normal and the most important thing you can do is do a lot of work.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Do a huge volume of work. Put yourself on a deadline so that every week or&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;every month you know you’re going to finish one story. It is only by going&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;through a volume of work that you’re going to catch up and close that gap.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;And the work you’re making will be as good as your ambitions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I took longer to figure out how to do this than anyone I’ve ever met. It&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;takes awhile. It’s gonna take you a while. It’s normal to take a while.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;You just have to fight your way through that.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;—Ira Glass&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure about you, but this explanation about the pursuit of evolving our
creativity made me have a light bulb moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think Glass perfectly describes why we shouldn’t “compare our beginning to
someone else’s middle” while at the same time sheds light on the true struggle
we as beginners go through while honing our creative skills (such as programming).
I also felt like the idea to create a volume of work in order to close the gap
really goes in hand with Malcolm Gladwell’s “10,000-Hour Rule”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apologies for the wall of text, I’ll stop here. If you’re more of a visual
learner, the comic Zen Pencils has an excellent interpretation of Ira Glass’
words.&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; Happy coding and hopefully some of you will
have found this as insightful as I did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EDIT&lt;/strong&gt;: I’m ecstatic that so many of you have found this advice helpful. I
made Glass’ advice into a nice little r/GetMotivated-esque poster.&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenpencils.com/comic/90-ira-glass-advice-for-beginners/&quot;&gt;https://zenpencils.com/comic/90-ira-glass-advice-for-beginners/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://i.redd.it/25ueejz4jj321.png&quot;&gt;https://i.redd.it/25ueejz4jj321.png&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[I Have Moved]]></title><description><![CDATA[No, I haven’t moved physically. Rather, I’ve moved my blog. My first blog,
 coffee. code. cedric , was hosted on Medium when that was the…]]></description><link>https://cedric.tech/blog/i-have-moved/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://cedric.tech/blog/i-have-moved/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 21:48:40 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;No, I haven’t moved physically. Rather, I’ve moved my blog. My first blog,
&lt;em&gt;coffee. code. cedric&lt;/em&gt;, was hosted on Medium when that was the cool thing to do.
I even had a custom domain for my publication before that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.medium.com/hc/en-us/articles/115003053487%0A-Custom-Domains-service-deprecation&quot;&gt;feature was steamrolled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I struggled with keeping the blog up-to-date. In many of my posts,
I would make commitments to write more often which turned out to never come true.
Not only that, I felt as though I had limited myself in the number of topics I
could write about since the original blog was geared towards programming and
Computer Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, when my old domain expired and the link to my Medium publication broke, I
decided to not fix it and instead told myself that I will host my own blog. Along
with that, I also made the decision to not limit myself in the type of content I
write about. What does that mean for this blog then? Well, anything goes. Be it
related to programming, philosophy, design, or my day, I won’t think twice and
worry about whether or not a post should belong on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I pretty much failed at having a blog before, I do enjoy writing (even
if I’m bad at it) and hope this blog will allow me to pursue this passion further.
So for now, I bid you adieu and I look forward to see where things go from here.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>