<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[My Random Thoughts]]></title><description><![CDATA[A collection of my random thoughts.]]></description><link>https://cedric.tech/blog</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2018 05:56:31 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[I Have Moved]]></title><description><![CDATA[No, I haven’t moved physically. Rather, I’ve moved my blog. My first blog,
 coffee. code. cedric , was hosted on Medium when that was the…]]></description><link>https://cedric.tech/blog/i-have-moved/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://cedric.tech/blog/i-have-moved/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 21:48:40 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;No, I haven’t moved physically. Rather, I’ve moved my blog. My first blog,
&lt;em&gt;coffee. code. cedric&lt;/em&gt;, was hosted on Medium when that was the cool thing to do.
I even had a custom domain for my publication before that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.medium.com/hc/en-us/articles/115003053487%0A-Custom-Domains-service-deprecation&quot;&gt;feature was steamrolled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I struggled with keeping the blog up-to-date. In many of my posts,
I would make commitments to write more often which turned out to never come true.
Not only that, I felt as though I had limited myself in the number of topics I
could write about since the original blog was geared towards programming and
Computer Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, when my old domain expired and the link to my Medium publication broke, I
decided to not fix it and instead told myself that I will host my own blog. Along
with that, I also made the decision to not limit myself in the type of content I
write about. What does that mean for this blog then? Well, anything goes. Be it
related to programming, philosophy, design, or my day, I won’t think twice and
worry about whether or not a post should belong on this blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I pretty much failed at having a blog before, I do enjoy writing (even
if I’m bad at it) and hope this blog will allow me to pursue this passion further.
So for now, I bid you adieu and I look forward to see where things go from here.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>